Finding aid for the Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company records, 1889-1991 LSC.1993
UCLA Library Special Collections
Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company records
1889-1991
bulk 1908-1922
UCLA Library Special Collections
Wilderness Land Trust
LSC.1993
23.4 Linear Feet (4 doc boxes, 2 half doc boxes, 1 flat box, 3 oversize flat boxes, 9 oversize map boxes)
The Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company was formed by Herman Henry Kerckhoff in Los Angeles in 1912. The company owned 2,450-acres of mining property in the Avawatz Mountains, located in the Mojave Desert of San Bernardino County. In 2011 the Wilderness Land Trust, a Colorado non-profit corporation, purchased the Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company and donated the land to the United States Bureau of Land Management for preservation. The collection contains a rich assortment of corporate document books, ledgers, and stock books; geologic and economic reports; mining-related government publications and newspaper articles; and geologic, structural, property, and railroad maps, tracing the history of this early southern California mining enterprise. Materials date from 1889 to 1991, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1908 to 1922.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by the Wilderness Land Trust in 2012.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9971089673606533
Biography/History
The Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company was formed in June of 1912 by Herman Henry Kerckhoff, a member of the prominent Los Angeles Kerckhoff family. Avawatz Salt and Gypsum was the final amalgamation of several earlier companies including the Death Valley Chemical Company (1908-1911), Avawatz Salt Company (1911-1912), and Avawatz Gypsum Company (1910-1912). The company owned 2,450 acres of land on the northeast edge of the Avawatz Mountains, at the southern end of Death Valley. This included, as of 1917, 50 mining claims and mineral deposits of gypsum, rock salt, and celestite. Kerckhoff intended to transport gypsum, the main ingredient in cement and wall plaster, from the Avawatz mines to nearby Los Angeles where it could be utilized in the ongoing building boom. To this end, the Amargosa Valley Railroad Company was formed in 1917 to construct a sixteen mile line connecting the Avawatz mines to the main railway leading to Los Angeles. Despite the Avawatz Company's large investment in engineering reports and land surveys, the outbreak of World War I made securing financing for the railroad difficult and it was never completed. Without the railroad connecting the remote mines to Los Angeles, Avawatz Company activity was for the most part halted. In 2011 the Wildness Land Trust, a Colorado nonprofit which buys and protects wilderness land, purchased the Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company from the Kerckhoff family and subsequently donated the land to the U.S. Department of the Interior Bureau of Land Management. The land is now part of the Death Valley Wilderness Study Area and falls within the boundaries of land which will be permanently preserved by Senator Diane Feinstein's pending California Desert Protection Act.
Scope and Content
This collection contains an assortment of corporate document books, ledgers, stock books, legal documents, and occasional correspondence from the Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company and its separate but related corporations - the Death Valley Chemical Company, Avawatz Salt Company, Avawatz Gypsum Company, Avawatz Sales Company, and the Amargosa Valley Railroad Company. Also included are mining-related government publications and newspaper articles; and a wealth of large geologic, structural, property, and railroad maps illustrating Avawatz land and the proposed Amargosa Valley Railroad. Particularly notable are several Avawatz commissioned economic and geologic reports featuring financial projections, photographs of the land, and detailed maps. Materials date from 1889 to 1991, with the bulk of the collection dating from ca. 1908 to 1922.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Business records, 1889-1991
Series 2: Reports and resource materials, 1908-1989
Series 3: Maps, 1911-1989
Series 1 is arranged chronologically by creating agency. Series 2 and 3 are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
Bodie Consolidated Mining Company Collection. California Department of Parks and Recreation, Sacramento, California.
Mining Companies Miscellany, California State Library. Box Number: 930-933
Patterson Mining Collection- Maps, 1848-1936. The Society of California Pioneers.
Wilderness Land Trust
- Series 1: Business records, 1889-1991
  Scope and Content
  Items comprising this series date from 1889-1991, with the bulk of the material dating from before 1922. The series consists of business records from The Death Valley Chemical Company, Avawatz Salt Company, Avawatz Gypsum Company, Avawatz Sales Company, and their amalgamation- the Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company. Records primarily take the form of bound volumes and include by-laws, meeting minutes, stock books, corporation books, ledgers, and journals. Also included are several volumes of legal abstracts from the San Bernardino Abstract Company, compiled at the request of the Death Valley Chemical Company in 1909. Additional loose documentation encompasses legal and financial papers such as deeds, location notices, proof of labor notices, real estate agreements, and correspondence.
  - Death Valley Chemical Company: By-laws, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Death Valley Chemical Company: Copy of by-laws, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Death Valley Chemical Company: Legal documents, resolutions, and other material, 1908-1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Death Valley Chemical Company: Meeting minutes, 1908-1911 (Box 7)
  - Death Valley Chemical Company: Stock book, 1908-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Death Valley Chemical Company: Stock book, 1908-1911 (Box 8)
  - Death Valley Chemical Company: Stock ledger, 1908-1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - San Bernardino Abstract Company: Legal document book, Volume 1, 1889-1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - San Bernardino Abstract Company: Legal document book, Volume 2, 1907-1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - San Bernardino Abstract Company: Legal document book, Volume 3, 1907-1909 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - San Bernardino Abstract Company: Legal document book, Volume 4, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Avawatz: Proof of labor, 1908-1922 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Avawatz: Legal documents and correspondence, 1909-1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Avawatz: Location notices, 1909-1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Avawatz Salt Company: Corporation book, 1910-1912 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contains inserted journal entries from Avawatz Gypsum Company.
  - Avawatz Salt Company: Letter sent, 1911 April 28 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Avawatz Sales Company: Corporation book, 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Cash records, 1912-1913 (Box 9)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: General ledger, 1912-1991 (Box 9)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Financial records, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Deed to Big Nitre and Gypsum King, 1917 August (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Original location notices, 1917 August (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Stock book, 1917 (Box 10)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Stock book, 1917-1920 (Box 10)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Journal 1-A, 1917-1921 (Box 10)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: Real estate agreements, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Company: General journal 2, 1922-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Amargosa Valley Railroad Company: Legal documents and report, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Reports and resource materials, 1909-1975
  This series consists of reports and resource materials dating from ca. 1908-1989, including government-issued bulletins and mineral reports, a book on mining law, and a magazine on excavation, as well as a collection of mining-related newspaper clippings. Also included are several early Avawatz commissioned geologic and economic reports which contain financial projections, photographs, and maps. Of particular note is the Lewis and Johnson Report (Box 8) for which many of the large maps in the collection were created. Later reproductions of some of these reports are also present and feature slightly different enclosures.
  - American Mining Law, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Geologic and Economic Report 1911 (copy), circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Avawatz Salt and Gypsum Geologic and Economic Report 1911 (copy with different enclosures), circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Department of the Interior: Bulletins, 1917-1923 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Department of the Interior: Mineral resources, 1910-1936 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Excavating Engineer magazine, 1939 February (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fault map of California, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Government publications, 1939-1942 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Lewis and Johnson Report, 1911 (Box 8)
  - List of Publications of the Bureau of Mines, July 1, 1910-January 1, 1949, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photographs accompanying Avawatz Property Report (1 of 2), circa 1909 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs accompanying Avawatz Property Report (2 of 2), circa 1909 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Report on Avawatz Mountains 1947 (copy), 1980s (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Resume of Information and Reports on Properties, circa 1914 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, 1911-1942 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - State Mineralogist reports, 1930-1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - T.L. Henderson Report, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Maps, 1911-1989
  Maps comprising this series were presumably commissioned by the Avawatz Company and include a number of large geologic, structural, property, and Union Pacific Railroad maps of Avawatz land. Also included are blueprints for proposed alterations to Herman Henry Kerckhoff's Laguna Niguel home in the 1970s. The majority of the items are in rolls, but a smaller amount of legal and letter size copies are also present, as are slides of the Union Pacific maps. Maps primarily date from 1911 or 1955, with reproductions dating into the 1980s. The 1911 maps accompanied the Lewis and Johnson Report (Box 8) of the same year.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Maps appear in several formats including white paper, linen, blueprint, negatives, auto positives, van dyke prints, transparencies, and photo prints. Some maps contain color.
  - 31655 Crystal Sands Drive alterations, circa 1972 (Box 11)
    Contains annotated blueprints and notes for additions to H.H. Kerckhoff Jr.'s home. 12 items.
  - Alteration Laguna Niguel, 1970s (Box 11)
    Contains blueprints and notes for H.H. Kerckhoff Jr.'s home. 6 items.
  - Avawatz entire property, circa 1942 (Box 12)
    10" x 19" small tracing on linen showing claim boundaries. 10" x 19" black negative, transparency copy, copy of positive showing whole property with section lines. Reductions of full size map including dimensions and section lines. 8 items.
  - Avawatz map of Valley and Boston, 1942 (Box 12)
    Linen. Final revision April 17, 1942. 1 item.
  - Avawatz maps (assorted copies), 1980s (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Includes copies of drilling logs.
  - Avawatz maps: Boston-Valley, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Avawatz maps: Outline, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes draft correspondence and newsletter.
  - Avawatz property map, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Folded large reproduction. 1 item.
  - Avawatz Union Pacific maps, circa 1955 (Box 15)
    Colored prints and auto positives. 11 items.
  - Cross section structural and geologic map- Lewis and Johnson Report, 1911 June (Box 11)
    White paper-blue line and black negative maps as used with the Lewis and Johnson report. Dated June 1911 but most likely reproductions. 3 items.
  - Geologic and structural map- Lewis and Johnson Report, 1911 June (Box 11)
    Original print 8.5" x 18" from June 1911. Photo print copy 12" x 24", undated. 2 items.
  - Lewis and Johnson prints of negatives, entire property and cross sections, 1911 June (Box 19)
    Linen and white prints, negative, and transparency. Dated June 1911 but may be reproductions. 15 items.
  - Map of entire property showing section lines, undated (Box 13)
    Black and white copies. 2 items.
  - Maps of entire Avawatz properties- original and autopositive, undated (Box 17)
    Avawatz properties full size black line on white, auto positive, and van dyke print for wet blue line. 6 items.
  - Original tracing structural sections accompanying report of Lewis and Johnson, 1911 June (Box 19)
    White paper-blue line. 2 items.
  - Print of original map (old), circa 1931 (Box 13)
    Print of Avawatz property with annotations dated through 1980. Contains typed set of notes by Porter T. Kerckhoff. 2 items.
  - Slides of Union Pacific Railroad map, 1979 April (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Survey of proposed railroad, undated (Box 16)
    Linen. 1 item.
  - Uncolored map- Lewis and Johnson Report, 1911 June (Box 16)
    Structural sections, geologic and structural, and structural sections small with color. Dated June 1911 but most likely reproductions. 3 items.
  - Union Pacific Railroad prints of colored drawings and Jumbo Salt Basin, 1955 (Box 18)
    Railroad, Salt Basin, West End, West End Celestite maps dated 1955. Boston-Valley Salt Claims undated maps. 8 items.
  - Union Pacific Report full size prints, no coloring, 1955 (Box 14)
    Includes D-1 Salt Basin, D-2 Boston-Valley (colored), D-3 Jumbo, D-4 West End, D-5 West End Celestite. Dated 1955 but may be reproductions. 20 items.